<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glasse for petitioners Wherein euery Christian man and woman, may cleerely see, what they are to beg at Gods hands, the manner how they are to beg, and the assurance of those things which they do beg. In a sermon preached at Framlingham Castle in high Suffolke. By Iohn Nevvman Master of Artes.</title>
            <author>Newman, John, fl. 1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113228</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848465</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13560</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08133)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13560)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glasse for petitioners Wherein euery Christian man and woman, may cleerely see, what they are to beg at Gods hands, the manner how they are to beg, and the assurance of those things which they do beg. In a sermon preached at Framlingham Castle in high Suffolke. By Iohn Nevvman Master of Artes.</title>
                  <author>Newman, John, fl. 1619.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffins for Iohn Barnes, and are to sold [sic] at his shop in Christ-Church walke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13560:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13560:1"/>
            <p>A LOOKING-GLASSE FOR PETITIONERS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein euery Chriſtian man</hi> and woman, may cleerely ſee, what they are to beg at Gods hands, the manner how they are to beg, and the aſſurance of thoſe things which they do beg.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached at <hi>Framlingham Caſtle</hi> in high Suffolke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN NEVVMAN <hi>Maſter of Artes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOH. 16.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hitherto haue yee asked nothing in my name: Aske, and yee ſhall receiue, that your ioy may be full.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Iohn Barnes,</hi> and are to ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> walke. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13560:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13560:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> HENRY MILDMAY <hi>Maſter of his Maieſties IEWELS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Litle thought of printing this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, when I preach't it, much leſſe of dedicating it to your Worſhip, after I had reſolued to print it. But I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded vnto the one, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:13560:3"/>
of my freinds and audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (who do better conceit of it then I my ſelfe): and I am emboldned vnto the other; firſt, <hi>quadam affinitate, by ſome ſmall alliance,</hi> which makes me to preſume more vpon you, then vpon any other. Secondly, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your Worſhips loue towards vertue &amp; learning, which, as moſt men ſay, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds your greatneſſe: and herein you do no whit dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate from your Anceſtors and forefathers, whoſe loue vnto learning did ſo abound, that their famous and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deeds, (of which both
<pb facs="tcp:13560:3"/>
the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and many other places, can teſtifie) do aeternize their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, in the Regiſter of euer-liuing fame: There let them liue, and may your Worſhip continue in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their foot-ſteps, that your vertues may as long continue alſo after your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequies. And as I am bold to preſent vnto you this ſmal gift, this plaine <hi>Looking glaſſe;</hi> ſo I humbly intreat your Worſhip, as willingly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it, and to looke in it, that being ſhrouded in the chamber of ſo worthy a Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleman, it may be kept from
<pb facs="tcp:13560:4"/>
being cracked by the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniations of cenſorious tongues. So ſhall I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all dutifull ſeruice J. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13560:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> LOOKING-GLASSE FOR PETITIONERS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVK. 11.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Aske, and it ſhall be giuen you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are part of a leſſon, which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt taught vnto his Diſciples; being deſirous how to pray aright that they might be heard. In the firſt verſe of this chapter one in the behalfe of the reſt puts vp this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. teach vs how to pray as <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo taught his diſciples. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond verſe he as a louing and carefull
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13560:5"/>
maſter as willing to profit his ſchollers, as they to learne: he ſets them downe this abſolute forme of prayer, teaching them what to aske, in theſe words when you pray ſay, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen &amp;c.</hi> As followeth vnto the 5. verſe. In which 5. verſe and in the 6.7.8. verſes: leaſt they ſhould be diſcouraged if they did not inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently and at the firſt, obtaine that which they prayed for: he bringeth the ſimilitude or parable of the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate borrower of three loaues of bread, teaching them not to be weary but to perſeuere in praier; and in this 9 verſe, in theſe words which I haue now reade vnto you leaſt they ſhould be fearefull, and ſo not pray at all, or faint harted and ſo make weake prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: he emboldens them, willing them to pray, and to be confident in prayer, giuing his word vnto them that he wil heare them: and promiſing that he will graunt their requeſts: <hi>Aske,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and it ſhall be geuen you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words I will obſerue two things, firſt an Inuitation in this word,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13560:5"/>
               <hi>Aske:</hi> ſecondly a promiſe, in theſe words, <hi>and it ſhall be giuen you.</hi> In the inuitation I will obſerue. <hi>Quid, and Quomodo; quid?</hi> what wee muſt aske, <hi>Quomodo?</hi> how wee muſt aske; in the promiſe, I will obſerue: the promiſer, and the thing promiſed; the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer God, the thing promiſed; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer wee ſhall aske; in the promiſer, I will obſerue firſt his abilitie: in that he is able to performe, whatſoeuer he promiſeth. Secondly his willingneſſe: in whatſoeuer he promiſeth he is will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to performe. In the thing promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: I will likewiſe obſerue theſe two two things; firſt the generallitie, in this word It. Secondly the certainty of it, in this word, <hi>Shall; It ſhall be giuen you; Aske, and it ſhall be giuen you.</hi> And firſt of the firſt thing obſerued, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitation, <hi>Quid?</hi> what wee muſt aske.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in a certaine home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaith, that the firſt condition of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is, that that which wee do aske, ought to be ſomthing; that when we doe pray we muſt pray for ſomthing; now his opinion is: that temporary
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13560:6"/>
matters, that the things which belong vnto the body, be nothing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not to be asked, but aboue all things he would haue vs ſeeke the kingdome of heauen and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes thereof and then al theſe things below ſhall be caſt vpon vs, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith that it was but one thing, that the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> did require of the Lord: <hi>Vnum petij</hi> Pſal. 27.4. <hi>one thing haue I deſired of the Lord, which I will require, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord; all the daies of my life; Qui vere chriſtianus eſt,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>non iſta temporalia appetere debet, ſed totum pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus orationis &amp; intentionis ſuae ad aeternam beatitudinem debet impendere; He that is a true chriſtian, ought not to aske and begg of God temporary matters, but the whole intent of all his prayers, ought to be beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in begging of the <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> the <hi>vnum neceſſarium, aeternall bleſſednes;</hi> but he thus expounds himſelfe ſaying, <hi>Sed tamen haec abſolute petenda non eſſe, intelligendum eſt; But not withſtanding it is to be vnderſtood: that theſe things ought to be asked; but not abſolutely;</hi> he doth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13560:6"/>
not ſay, that we muſt not aske them at all, but he ſaith we muſt aske them ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, and conditionally and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely, not at all in reſpect of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bleſſings theſe temporary matters are not to be asked; temporary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings wee may pray for, but aboue all things, let vs aske of God thoſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall graces which will bring vs to the kingdome of heauen. <hi>Ecce alius in ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Gregorie) poſtulat veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: alius ſibi dari alimentum et: quidem ſi haec deſint, ab omnipotenti deo, ſunt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda: haec petere, non eſt errare, ſed tamen non nimie petantur; one</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>deſires of God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his prayer raiment, and clothing, another begs for food, and nouriſhment, theſe things if they be wanting, muſt be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the almighty God; to begg them is no ſinne, but yet wee muſt not too greedily deſire them.</hi> But <hi>Barnard de oratione,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though mellifluouſly, yet plainely comes vnto the matter: for he ſets downe what wee muſt pray for, and alſo the condition of our prayers what they muſt be: <hi>The prayers of the heart</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I doe beleeue do conſiſt in theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13560:7"/>
three things; neither doe I ſee what elſe beſides theſe three things any child of God can pray for: two of which concernes this world: the third concernes the world to come;</hi> all that wee can pray for, in this world, is that God would beſtow vpon vs, the goods of our bodyes &amp; ſoules, all outward bleſſings neceſſarie for the body, and all inward graces conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the ſoule, and all that wee can deſire in the world to come: is <hi>aeternall Bleſſedneſſe:</hi> that God as he hath giuen vs the kingdome of grace: ſo he would giue vs the kingdome of glory; that he would in his good time bring vs out of this tranſitory world to his perpetuall kingdome, there to raigne with him world without end. And therfore wee pray <hi>Thy kingdome come.</hi> There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe that wee can pray for; All our prayers tend to this end that whilſt wee liue in this world, wee may haue ſufficient nouriſhment for our bodyes ſpirituall foode for our ſoules, and in the world to come, wee may haue life euerlaſting. And in begging of theſe three things, three things muſt be auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13560:7"/>
in the firſt, <hi>Superfluitas;</hi> in the ſecond, <hi>Impuritas;</hi> in the third, <hi>Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantia.</hi> In the firſt, <hi>ſuperfluitie;</hi> we muſt aske of God thoſe things onely, which be neceſſary, for our bodies. In the ſecond, <hi>Impuritie;</hi> we muſt not aske and beg of God, ſpirituall graces, to brag and boaſt of them. In the third, <hi>Pride and arrogancie;</hi> not ſeeking ſaluation in our owne works and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but in the mercies of God, and in the merits of our Sauiour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer Chriſt Ieſus. In the firſt, in beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of things for the bodie, we muſt auoide ſuperfluitie: for God will not grant our greedy deſires; neither will he liſten vnto our prayers, if we doe not aske thoſe things, which be meete for him to giue, and conuenient for vs to receiue. <hi>In oratione</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedine) duo ſpectanda: In prayer there are two things to be conſidered; neceſſitas vel decorum;</hi> the neceſſitie of thoſe things which we aske; and the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and meetnes of them: the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie (that is) thoſe things which concerne the ſuſtentation, the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13560:8"/>
the health, the freedome, and liberties of our bodies. Foode and clothing, health and liberty, is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for our bodies: and theſe things muſt be asked of God, and ſo much of them, as will ſuffice, and no more: If we aske more then will ſuffice, to ſpend vpon our pleaſures, or to ſatisfie our luſts, we ſhall not be heard, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we aske amiſſe: <hi>Yee aske and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Iames</hi> 4.3.) <hi>becauſe you aske amiſſe,</hi> that yee might conſume it on your luſts. We muſt pray, as our Sauiour Chriſt commandeth vs; <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem noſtrum quotidianum, da nobis hodie, Giue vs this day our daily bread:</hi> that is, giue vs thoſe things, which be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent both for our bodies and ſoules; giue vs the ſtaffe of bread, which is ſufficient for our bodies; giue vs Chriſt, which is the bread of the faithfull, the foode of our ſoules; giue vs <hi>panem praeter panem &amp; ſuper panem, aboue bread and beſides bread; Da nobis vtrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> panem corporis &amp; animae, giue vs foode both for the body and ſoule.</hi> This I take to be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13560:8"/>
of the words in generall. But if we come to handle the words in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; we ſhall finde that theſe three words, <hi>panem, noſtrum, quotidianum,</hi> affords vs three ſpeciall doctrines, fit for our purpoſe; for whereas he ſaies <hi>Pan m,</hi> he bids vs aske for bread which is the common ſuſtinance for our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, he would haue vs to be content with that which the Lord ſends: and not to luſt after the fleſh pots of <hi>Egipt,</hi> to be fed with delicates and fare delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly euery day, for if wee haue bread, if we haue wherewithall to ſatiſfie our hunger, to quench our thirſtes, and to clothe our bodyes; wee muſt learne with the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> therewithall to be content. And whereas he ſaith, <hi>panem noſtrum,</hi> our bread he would haue vs to be content with that which is ours, which is our owne, and not too greedily deſire that which is other mens: he would not haue vs to liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vſurie, oppreſſion, theft, deceipt, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood, he would not haue vs, ſo much as to couet our neighbours goods: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their Oxen, nor their aſſes, their man-ſeruants
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13560:9"/>
or their maide ſeruants, their wiues or their cattle nor any thing which belongs vnto them; much leſſe by force or violence, by craft or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſteale, or to purloine any thing from them: but to be content with that which is our owne: deſiring of the Lord only <hi>(panem noſtrum) our bread</hi> and no more. And wheras, he ſaith, <hi>panem noſtrum quotidianum, our daily bread,</hi> he would not haue vs be too carefull for the time to come, for what wee ſhall eat, and what wee ſhall drinke and where withall wee ſhall be clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed; but to take that which is preſent thankfully, confidently repoſing and putting our truſt, in the Almighty, that no want ſhall happen vnto vs, in regard wee haue him for our louing father, who will be as carefull ouer vs as wee can be ouer our ſelues: neither would he haue vs to be gluttons, and drunkards, and eate and drinke as much in one day, as would ſerue for many dayes; but he would haue vs to be ſober and temperate, and take no more in the day, then will ſerue for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13560:9"/>
day: auoiding all ſuperfluitie, taking that only which is neceſſarie, no more we muſt vſe no more wee muſt pray for, if wee do our p ayers ſhalbe in vaine, wee ſhall not be heard, <hi>becauſe wee aſke amiſſe.</hi> And as wee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the neceſſi ie, ſo alſo muſt wee keepe a <hi>decorum</hi> in our prayers. Wee muſt aske of God that, which is meete for him to giue and conuenient for vs to receiue; all ſuperſtitious, all wicked, vniuſt, curious, raſh, preſumptuous, &amp; vnprofitable prayers muſt be laide a ſide; and in all our prayers the ſpecial thing wee muſt aime at is the glory of God; that thoſe things, which wee pray for may be to Gods glory and our owne comfort. The prayer of the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Zebedeus</hi> children, was vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe it was full of ambition, for ſhee dreaming of a temporall king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome deſired of our Sau our Chriſt honor and preferment for her ſonns, that the one might ſitt on his right hand th'other on his left hand in his kingdome; <hi>Mat: the.</hi> 20.21. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viour Chriſt anſwered her with <hi>Neſcitis
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13560:10"/>
quid petitis, you know not what you aske,</hi> rebuking them for their preſumption for asking thoſe things, which were not meete, for him to giue, and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for them to receiue. The requeſt alſo of <hi>Herodias</hi> daughter who asked of the king, <hi>Iohn Baptiſts head,</hi> was not to the glory of God; but altogether a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bominable and vnlawfull and if we muſt not deſire of men thoſe things which be vnlawfull: much leſſe of our heauenly father. Yf ſhee might not aske <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> head of the king; who was her mothers enemie: much leſſe ought wee to deſire of God, the hurt, deſtruction, or confuſion of our ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies as they bee our owne enemies. Indeed, if in being our enemies, they be the enemies of God: then wee may pray with the prophet <hi>Dauid: Oh Lord confound our foes, let ſhame and confuſion ſmite them, ſo that they may not be able to preuaile againſt thee and againſt thine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed;</hi> but the deprecations that wee daily vſe, the curles and the plagues, which wee pray for, to light vpon one anothers heads, nay, and vpon our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13560:10"/>
ſelues be moſt fearefull and moſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable; we pray the plague, the pox, the gallowes, ſudden death and a l manner of punniſhments, to light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues and others: whereas if God were not more mercifull in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and granting, then wee be in deſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring, there is no day but many of vs ſhould be conſumed: there is no hower but many of vs ſhould periſh; there is no minute of an hower, but many of vs ſhould haue one puniſhment or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light vpon vs; <hi>Epicurus</hi> was wont to ſay, as<note n="*" place="margin">Maximius</note> 
               <hi>Maximius</hi> reports: <hi>breui ſpatio homines omnes perituros eſſe, ſi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum preces ſequeretur deus; that in a little time, all men ſhould periſh, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be conſumed, if God ſhould grant all men their deſires;</hi> and his reaſon is this, <hi>quoniam multa &amp; acerba alij in alios pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cantur; becauſe men pray ſo bitterly one againſt another.</hi> If he might ſay ſo in his time: well wee may ſay ſo in our times: vpon whome the latter ends of the world be come: amongſt whome iniquitie abounds; for, whereas wee ſhould pray for our enemies, and for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13560:11"/>
one another, either wee neglect it, and pray not at all: or elſe wee pray for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to light vpon them; witneſſe the continuall &amp; common deprecations, which be as riſe in mens mouthes, as their ordinary talking For which of vs amongſt vs, (I ſpeake of the moſt part of vs) doth not curſe his enemie? nay curſe his friend? nay, the fruit of our owne bodies? wee do not ſpare, but many of vs commonly curſe and bann our owne children: nay, our ſelues wee curſe: wiſhing plagues to light vpon our bodyes, our ſoules, wee do not ſpare, but many of vs commonly wiſh damnation vnto them; which prayers and curſes if the Lord ſhould heare, (as no queſtion but he doth heare them) but if he ſhould grant them, fearefull and lamentable were our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates? beloued; he doth grant them, &amp; many times according to our owne harts deſire, our bodyes conſume and come to vntimely ends; our wealth decayes and no way proſpers; our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren turne diſobedient riotous, vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and euill conditioned, &amp; our ſoules
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13560:11"/>
are finally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in hell fire; how feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and lamentable be theſe our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? and yet how ordinarily do wee vſe them? which of vs (if wee examine our ſelues) be free from them? take heed, and take the pſalmiſts councell; <hi>ſtand in awe and ſinne not;</hi> Be carefull how thou makeſt ſuch prayers vnto God; for as ſure as he liueth in heauen, he will heare them, and will ſend ſuch plagues &amp; curſes vpon thee and thine as thou deſireſt: vnleſſe thou ſpeedily repent, ſuch prayers wee muſt not vſe, for they be neither meet nor conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, meete for God to heare, conueni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent for vs to receiue, rather let vs pray with the heathen man: <hi>Da bona ſiue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare deus ſeu nulla petare &amp; procul a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis mala quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> petentibus aufer, &amp; mala ſiue petare nega, ſeu nulla petare. Grant oh Lord that wee may pray for ſuch things as be to thy glory, or elſe that wee may not pray at all: and remoue farre from vs, wee beſeech thee, all wicked prayers, either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vs thoſe things, which be hurtfull and not conuenient for vs, or elſe grant, that wee may make no ſuch prayers vnto thee.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13560:12"/>
And as in praing for temporary mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters: wee muſt reſpect the neceſſitie, &amp; keepe a <hi>Decorum:</hi> ſo in praying for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces, and for life euerlaſting wee muſt reſpect th'end, why we pray and the manner how wee pray: wee muſt not pray for ſpirituall graces, to the end wee may be puffed vp, and ſo bragg and boaſt of them, as Hypocrits doe; for then the Lord will not heare vs; neither muſt wee ſeeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, relying vpon our owne workes, and merits: as did the proud Phariſie, for then the Lord will not regard vs, but with the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> let vs begg for the graces need full for our ſoules in all ſimplicitie: and with the <hi>Publican</hi> for the kingdome of heauen in all humilitie: and then the Lord will giue vs thoſe things which we deſire, and then he will heare vs in thoſe things which we pray for: <hi>Aske,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt) and it ſhall be giuen you</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt thing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in the invitation; <hi>Quid,</hi> what we muſt aske: the ſecond thing obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, is <hi>Quomodo,</hi> how we muſt aske.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13560:12"/>
For as the Lord will not heare vs, if we doe not aske thoſe things, which be meet and conuenient: ſo he will not grant our requeſts, vnleſſe we pray as we ought to doe; therefore it is very neceſſarie, for vs to learne how to pray. Now if we will pray as we ought to do, we muſt pray after this manner, <hi>Innocenter, humiliter, fideliter, amanter, conſtanter,</hi> and <hi>audacter;</hi> innocently, humbly, faithfully, louingly, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and boldly: for if with our prayers, theſe ſix vertues be not ioyned, <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cencie, humilitie, faith, charitie, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> and <hi>courage,</hi> our prayers can be to no effect: neither can they enter into the Lords eares. For the two firſt: <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie</hi> and <hi>Humilitie,</hi> be the wings of prayer, whereby our prayers pierce the skies, and aſcend to heauen gates. The ſecond two, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Charitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> be the keyes of heauen gates, to let in our prayers when they are aſcended: and the third two, <hi>Conſtancie</hi> and <hi>boldnes,</hi> be prayers aduocates to deliuer our praiers vnto the Lords eares, and to plead for ſuch things as we pray for.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13560:13"/>
Now if they want <hi>Innocencie</hi> or <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> our prayers cannot aſcend: for they cannot flie without wings, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will one winge ſuffice them to flie withall: If they want <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi> they cannot enter into heauen gates, although they do aſcend; for heauen gates cannot be opened with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe two keyes: neither can one key open them. And if they want <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie</hi> and <hi>boldnes,</hi> they cannot enter into the Lords eares; for vnleſſe theſe two preferre them, the Lord will liſten to no petitions, neither dare one of theſe, come in Gods preſence without the other. So that we may ſee, if any one of theſe vertues be wanting, we had as good not to pray at all; for our prayers ſhall be in vaine; and if with our prayers, theſe ſix vertues be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, pray for what we will, <hi>(ſecundum voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) according to his will,</hi> our pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers ſhall be heard, our requeſts ſhall be granted; he himſelfe doth promiſe it, <hi>Aske,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>it ſhall be giuen you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, ſay, we muſt pray with <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie,</hi> with pure hearts, cleane hands,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13560:13"/>
innocent tongues, with hearts purified from idle thoughts, and world y cogi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations: <hi>Longe est enim à Deo animus qui in oratione cogitationibus ſaeculi est occupatus: For that heart is farre from God, which in the time of prayer is buſied with the cares of this world.</hi> With hands waſhed from euill works, from all manner of wickednes and vngodlines; <hi>Citius enim ad preces index flectitur, ſi peccator à prauitate ſua corrigatur: For the iudge is ſooner moued to liſten vnto vs, when he ſees our liues to be amended:</hi> with tongues ſeaſoned with godly ſpeeches, <hi>Niſi enim lingua ſit pura, orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones impuras eſſe neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt: For vnles our tongues be pure, it must needs be that our prayers muſt be altogether vnholy.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we come to pray, we muſt come with repentant hearts, with ſoules and bodies waſhed cleane, with the teares of repentance, hating the ſinnes that we haue committed, hating our ſelues for committing of ſin, then our prayers ſhall be offered vpon the Altar of our hearts, as the Lambe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar of the Tabernacle <hi>Exo:</hi> 2.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13560:14"/>
without ſpot or blemiſh: Then our prayers will ſmell ſweet, will be as a ſweet ſauour in Gods noſtthrills; then our prayers will be powerfull, and will wreſt bleſſings from the Lord: Nay then the Lord will willingly heare vs, and will willingly grant our requeſts: <hi>Si enim obedierimus Deo, obediet Deus orationibus noſtris: If wee ſerue God, God will not faile, but he will be ſure to ſerue vs.</hi> But if we come vnto him, in the midſt of our ſinnes, hauing our hearts polluted with wicked imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, our tongues poyſoned with odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blaſphemies, and our hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeared with the blood of his onely ſonne, with the blood of Innocents, being full of wrongs and oppreſſions; heare what the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith 1.15. <hi>When you ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you; yea when you make many prayers, I will not heare you.</hi> Now we know that the Lord will not heare ſinners, ſaith <hi>S. Iohn</hi> 2.31. But as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> will not be taken with the ſinging voice of a corrupt, but of a pure Virgin: and as the fiſh, will not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13560:14"/>
come into or ſuffer it ſelfe to be inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in an impure veſſell, which is be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore moyſtned, and beſmeared with the blood of other fiſhes: So the Lord will not (as we may ſay) be taken, with the hymnes, pſalmes nor ſongs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the prayers of the wicked, and vngodly; neither is he inclined to heare thoſe, whoſe hands be imbrued with cruelty, with wrongs and iniuries, and the blood of poore innocents. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> often ſung vnto the Lord, often cryed, often faſted, and often prayed, yet heare what he ſaith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.8. <hi>If I regard iniquitie in my heart, the Lord will not heare me.</hi> For as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neque ietunium, neque ſilentium, neque vigilia, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> orationes, &amp; alia bona opera grata ſunt Deo, vbi virtus obedientiae deest: Neither faſting, nor ſilence, nor watching, nor praying, neither any good workes, are acceptable vnto God. if obedience vnto his lawes he wanting in vs:</hi> for to obey is better then ſacrifice, to harken is better then the fat of Lambes. Therefore when we come to pray, with <hi>Dauid</hi> let vs waſh our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13560:15"/>
hands in innocencie, let vs clenſe our prayers in the deepe ſighes of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let vs waſh them in the watery eares of Attrition, and embrue them in vertuous actions, and in holy cogitations, then they will ſhine in the Lords ſight, then they will ſound in the Lords eares, then they will turne vnto vs not empty, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with many bleſſings.</p>
            <p>The ſecond vertue, that we muſt ioyne with our prayers, is <hi>Humilitie;</hi> thy prayers muſt be humble; thou muſt pray, <hi>verecundo affectu,</hi> not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſpeake vnto the Lord, with the woman, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. <hi>Et duro affectu,</hi> not daring to appeare in his ſight, with the woman <hi>Luk.</hi> the 7. In the 8 of <hi>Luke,</hi> the woman who had the iſſue of blood, being aſhamed to ſpeake to IESVS; ſhe durſt no more but touch the hemme of his garment: and <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> in the 7. of <hi>Luke,</hi> being aſhamed to appeare in his preſence, ſhee ſtood behind him weeping, being wonderfully affectioned, ſhee waſhed his feete vvith her teares, and vviped
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13560:15"/>
them with the haires of her head. When we pray, let vs be aſhamed of our ſelues, let vs be aſhamed to come before God, let vs ſtand a far off, with the Publican, let vs hold downe our heads, knock our breſts, and iudge our ſelues altogether vnworthy to bee heard, or to be regarded of the Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mighty, and then our prayers from our lowly hearts, will no queſtion flie vnto the higheſt heauens: <hi>Nam quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do humilis oratio fuerit,</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard) coelum ſine dubio penetrabit, vnde certum est, quod vacua redire non poſſit; When our prayer is humble, it will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, pierce into the highest heauens, from whence it can by no meanes returne empty. Let me ſpeake vnto the Lord, who am but dust and aſhes,</hi> ſaith the holy father <hi>Abraham:</hi> He vvas a holy Patriarke, a man of great ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, one beloued of God, one vvho vvas reputed faithfull, and one in vvhoſe ſeede all the nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed; yet vvee may ſee, hovv in his prayer he humbleth himſelfe; he brags not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13560:16"/>
of his riches, he boaſts not in his good workes, he glories not in his promiſed poſteritie, but acknowledgeth from whence he came, namely, out of the earth; he confeſſeth what he is, made of, <hi>Duſt and Aſhes;</hi> and as duſt and aſhes he humbles himſelfe at Gods feete, before he durſt make his praier vnto him: <hi>Haec est vera oratio this is true prayer,</hi> which is made in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: ſo ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> in his <hi>Mor: Ille Deo veram orationem exhibet, qui ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metipſum cognoſcit, quia puluis humiliter vi it, qui nihil ſibi virtutis tribuit, qui bona quae ugit, eſſe de miſericordia condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris agnoſcit: He prayes rightly vnto God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which knowes himſelfe to be but iust and aſhes, who attributes no goodnes vnto himſelfe, but aſcribes all vnto his Lord and maker.</hi> So did the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> who makes himſelfe a worme and no man, he makes himſelf a worme the leaſt of all creatures, and by that meanes, becomes to be one of the greateſt in Gods fauour: He ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and acknowledged his ſinnes, he prai'd in all humilitie, and by his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13560:16"/>
confeſſion and lowly prayers, he obtained pardon for all his tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. So muſt we pray, if we will be heard, if we will haue our prayers aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend: wee muſt deſcend, not downe into earth, but caſt our ſelues vpon the earth: wee muſt become lowly in our owne eies, and little in our owne conceipts, if wee will haue our prayers mount, if with the archer wee will haue our arrowe fly very high, if wee will haue our prayers fly to the higheſt: wee muſt bend backward very low, wee muſt humble our ſelues in all hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>militie and then they will pierce the skies, for the praiers of him that hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bleth himſelfe, (ſayth the ſonne of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach) Eccle:</hi> 35.14. <hi>goeth through th clouds, and ceaſeth not vntill it come neere: and will not depart vntill the moſt high haue reſpect thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third vertue that wee muſt ioyne with our prayers is faith, wee muſt <hi>Credere Deum,</hi> wee muſt beleiue that there is a God that doth heare our prayers and wee muſt <hi>Credere Deo,</hi> wee muſt beleeue that God, who doth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13560:17"/>
heare our prayers, will performe our requeſts, it he ſhall ſee them conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for vs: If we do not beleeue there is a God, how ſhall we call vpon him; <hi>How ſhall they call vpon him, in whom they haue not beleeued?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 10.14. And if we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that this God will heare vs, and will grant our requeſts, let vs neuer looke to receiue any bleſſing, ſo ſaith <hi>S. Iames,</hi> ſpeaking of the wauering-minded man; <hi>Let not that man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thinke that he ſhall receiue any thing of the Lord, Iam.</hi> 1.7. <hi>If any man lacke wiſdome, let him aske, and it ſhall be giuen him: But let him aske in faith, and wauer not, for he that wauereth</hi> (as you may read in the former verſes) <hi>is like vnto the waues of the ſea toſſed in the winde, and caried away,</hi> he is vnconſtant in all his actions, and therefore vnconſtant in all his prayers; hee beleeues euery thing, and therefore he beleeues no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: as the waues of the ſea be toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed here and there, and ſeldome at quiet; ſo his minde neuer reſts vpon one thing, but he is ſubiect to much
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13560:17"/>
variablenes, for now he thinks he ſhall be heard, preſently he thinks not, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he thinks that there is a God, another time doubts whether there be or no; at one time he make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of Gods abilitie and all-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, another time he makes a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as in his actions doeth plainely appeare, whether God can heare if his neceſſitie ſhould require. How can God heare this man, who is ſo ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of him? he cannot heare him: and why? becauſe he doth not pray; for prayer without faith, is no prayer at all. <hi>Sola enim fides invocat ea<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſola impetrat, fieri enim poteſt vt citra fidem quis Deo placeat: For it is faith onely that prayes, it is faith onely that calls vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, and without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe him. Hebr.</hi> 11.6. <hi>for he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to God muſt beleeue that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that ſeek him.</hi> Therefore ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.24. <hi>I ſay vnto yee, whatſoeuer you deſire when you pray, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that yee ſhall haue it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be done vnto you.</hi> This counſell the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13560:18"/>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.6. <hi>I haue called vpon thee, ô God, for thou ſhalt heare me:</hi> and in the 55.17. <hi>As for me I will call vpon God, and the Lord ſhal ſaue me.</hi> He prayed without wauering, he prayed without doubting; he was ſo confident in prayer, that he ſaid the Lord ſhould heare him: he bindes God to performe that which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth. God promiſeth to heare all thoſe who faithfully call vpon him, and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> according to Gods promiſe will be heard. This counſell of our Sauiour Chriſt let vs alſo embrace, that which we pray for, let vs make no queſtion but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; let not the leaſt doubt at all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into vs; let vs pray without doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and then without doubt we ſhall be heard.</p>
            <p>The fourth vertue that we muſt ioyne with our prayers is <hi>Charitie;</hi> and if we will haue this vertue Charitie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie our prayers, <hi>dandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt egen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, ignoſcendum est delinquentibus &amp; orandum eſt pro omnibus: We muſt giue to others, we muſt forgiue others, and we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13560:18"/>
muſt pray for others.</hi> We muſt giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others, we muſt ioyne with our prayers, Almes; and then our prayers and our Almes ſhall come vp into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance before God, as did the prayers and Almes of <hi>Cornelius, Act:</hi> 10. Then our prayers will enter into the Lords eares, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58.7. <hi>Deale thy bread to the hungry; bring the poore that wander vnto thine houſe, and when thou ſeeſt the naked couer him, then ſhalt thou call, and the Lord ſhall anſwer, thou ſhalt cry, and he ſhall ſay, here I am.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we muſt forgiue others, if we our ſelues will be forgiuen, we muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs: It is a petition we daily vſe, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</hi> Thus we ſay: <hi>Sed vide quid dicas</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe) quomodo dimitto ſic &amp; tu dimitte mihi, ſi dimiſeris, bene conuenit vt dimittat tibi: ſi non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeris, quomodo convenit vt tibi dimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat? Take heede and marke well what thou ſayest, as I forgiue, ſo doe thou O Lord forgiue me; if thou doeſt forgiue, it agrees well that God ſhould forgiue thee:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13560:19"/>
but if thou doſt not forgiue, it doth not agree with Gods Iuſtice to forgiue thee thy ſinnes committed against him.</hi> If thou doſt not forgiue, thou ſhalt not be forgiuen; if thou ſheweſt no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, thou ſhalt finde no mercy in the time of neede; <hi>for there ſhall be iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mercileſſe to him that ſheweth no mercy,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Iames.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Quod ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus metimus, quod damus accipimus: That which we ſowe we ſhall reape, that which we giue we ſhall receiue.</hi> If wee ſowe no forgiueneſſe, we ſhall reape none; if we giue no forgiueneſſe, no forgiueneſſe ſhall be giuen vnto vs when we pray for it. Therefore ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.25. <hi>But when you ſhall ſtand and pray forgiue, if you haue any thing against any man, that your Father alſo which is in heauen may forgiue you your treſpaſſes: for if you will not forgiue, your Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen will not pardon you your treſpaſſes.</hi> Thirdly, wee muſt pray for others: We muſt pray for all men, firſt of all ſorts: <hi>I will that first of all ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and prayers, interceſſions and giuing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13560:19"/>
of thanks be made for all men, for Kings and all that are in authoritie;</hi> for all men: that is, for all that be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of election, for thoſe that be of the houſhold of Faith: For all men, that is, for all men in generall: for if we be bound by the words of the Apoſtle to <hi>doe good vnto all men,</hi> I ſee no reaſon, no more doe many other Diuines, which I haue read vpon this place, but that likewiſe we ſhould pray for all men; be they either Turkes, infidels, heathen, the enemies of God, or the enemies of our ſelues; we muſt pray for their conuerſion, if it be the will of God, that they may be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But moſt eſpecially we that be Chriſtians, we that be of the houſhold of Faith, we ought to pray for one another; Charitie bids vs, God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands vs: <hi>Non dicimus, pater meus,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cyprian de orat: Dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) ſed noſter, nec da mihi, ſed da nobis, quia Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis magiſter, noluit pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atim precem fieri, vt ſcilicet quis proſe tant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: vnum enim orare pro omnibus vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit, quando in vno omnes ipſe portauit.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13560:20"/>
We doe not ſay when we pray, as Christ hath commanded vs, my Father, but our Father; nor, giue vnto me, but giue vnto vs: becauſe he that is maſter of Chriſti anitie, would not that priuate prayer ſhould be made, that is, that a man ſhould pray for himſelfe onely, or for his priuate houſhold: but he would haue vs to pray for all in one, becauſe as all in one he hath borne our infirmities.</hi> And the ſame Father writing vpon <hi>Matthew,</hi> vſeth theſe words: <hi>Pro ſe orare neceſſitas co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, pro alijs autem Charitas fraternitatis hortatur: To pray for our ſelues, neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie compells vs; to pray for others, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Chatitie exhorts vs.</hi> Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we doe pray, pray not only for our ſelues, but for others; not only for our friends, but for our enemies; not only for ſome particular men, but for all men in generall. <hi>Pray for one another</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Iames) that ye may be healed, for the praier of the righteous man auaileth much if it be feruent. Iam.</hi> 5.16.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, we muſt pray with conſtancie, with perſeuerance, holding out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end: <hi>Pray continually</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Theſſal:</hi> 5.17. that is,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13560:20"/>
continue in prayer: not all the time of your liues; for the Wiſeman ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1. <hi>That to all things there is an appointed time, a time to be borne, a time to dye, a time to plant, and a time to plucke vp that which is planted, a time to weepe and a time to laugh.</hi> But he would haue vs ſpend as much time as may be in prayer: we muſt with our Sauiour if need require, ſpend whole nights in prayer: we muſt with <hi>Daniel,</hi> pray thrice a day, in the morning, at noone, and at night: wee muſt begin our worke with prayer, goe forward with prayer, end it with prayer: and not onely doe thus one day, but all the daies of our liues; we muſt hold out vnto the end, and then we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the crowne. Let perſeuerance plead for thee, and then thou ſhalt be ſurely heard: leaue not the Lord, but call vpon him continually from time to time, and at the end he will heare thee. The <hi>Cananitiſh</hi> woman with her conſtancie and perſeuerance in calling vpon Chriſt, moued him to heale her daughter: the borrower of three
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13560:21"/>
loaues of bread, with his often knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, obtained his requeſt: and the widdow with her importunitie, moued the vnrighteous Iudge, to doe her iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: And ſhall not God auenge his? ſhall he not heare his Elect, which day and night call vpon him? yea though he ſuffer them long, I tell you he will auenge them, he will heare them, and that quickly. If we continue to call vpon God, he will heare vs although not at the firſt time, yet at the ſecond; if not at the ſecond, yet at the third; if not at the third time, yet at many times; if not at many times, yet once amongſt many times he will heare. And if he once heare vs, we ſhall be ſure to haue, that which is conuenient for vs; and if before he had ſeene it neceſſarie for vs, we ſhould without all queſtion haue had it. <hi>Fideliter enim ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicans Deo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aug. in lib. Sent:) mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericorditer auditur, &amp; miſericorditer non auditur, quid enim infirmo ſit vtilius, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit magis medicus quam aegrotus: He that makes his faithfull and humble ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication vnto God, in mercy he is heard,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13560:21"/>
and in mercy he is not heard: becauſe he who is the phiſition of our ſoules knowes better what is needfull for vs, then wee who be his weake patients.</hi> Therefore let vs be conſtant in calling vpon God and continue to cry vnto him: knowing that although he tarry long, that yet at laſt he will heare vs to our greater benefit.</p>
            <p>Sixtly and laſtly we muſt pray with courage, with boldneſſe, the Deuill muſt not ſcare vs, deſperation muſt not out face vs, our ſinns muſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may vs: but throwing downe the deuil, caſting aſide deſperation, treading downe our ſinns vnder our feete, let vs runn vnto our redeemer, fly vnto the mercies of our creator, and lay hold vpon them: then let the deuill roare againſt thee l ke a roring lion, deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration aſſault thee like a helliſh hagg, and thy ſinnes encounter thee like ſo manie enemies, yet thou needs not feare, for thy redeemer will defend thee, &amp; the mercy of thy creator will ouer-ſhadow thee, though the Deuill whiſper in thy conſcience &amp; tell thee,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13560:22"/>
that it is needleſſe for thee to pray, yet pray: the Deuill is a lyar, be not ruled by him: though deſperation tell thee that there is no hope of pardon; yet for all that pray for pardon &amp; beleeue me thou ſhalt haue it: though thy ſins ſay they be greater then can be forgi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen: <hi>mentiuntur peccata, thy ſinnes lie;</hi> for the mercies of God be greater then thy ſinns, if they were ten thouſand more then they bee. If thou be'ſt bold, and of a ſtout courage, the deuill can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hurt thee, for as <hi>Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius</hi> reports, the <hi>Deuill hurts none, but the faint-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> And if thou doſt confidently truſt in the mercies of God, thou ſhalt be ſaued, let thy ſinns and deſperation do what they can againſt thee. Pray bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and the Lord will heare thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou beeſt in depth of miſery, yet he wil heare thee in height of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye. <hi>Si turbata fuerit anima</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>memor eſto multitudinis miſericordiae eius, &amp; reſpira in eum. If thy mind be troubled, be mindfull of the mercies of God: and ſtay thy ſelfe vpon them.</hi> By all meanes be not faint hearted, for <hi>ex pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimitate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13560:22"/>
spiritus, &amp; timore immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rato, impeditur oratio.</hi> For there is no greater enemie vnto thy prayers, then <hi>faint heartedneſſe and immoderate feare. Qui enim timide rogat docet negare: for he that asketh fearefully, teacheth him of whom hee beggs how to denie him.</hi> Pray therefore boldly and with a confident corage, ſeeke to thy creator: although in reſpect of thy ſelfe and thy ſinnes, thou mayeſt feare: yet in reſpect thou haſt a louing Sauiour, and a mercifull creator, thou mayſt be bold: let bold<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe pleade for thee, and then thou mai'ſt be bold to expect thy deſires, for boldneſſe will haue no deniall, but will be heard.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I ſhewed you how we muſt pray in reſpect of the inward man, the outward manner of praying, the Lord doth not ſo much regard: I meane the outward geſture of ours, which wee vſe when we do pray: ſome when they pray fall vpon their knees, as <hi>Daniell</hi> when he p ayed thrice a day our Sauiour Chriſt, when he prayed in the garden: &amp; <hi>Paule</hi> when he pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13560:23"/>
for the church of the gentiles: <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3. others lift vp their hands to heauen: as <hi>Salomon.</hi> 1. <hi>kings.</hi> 8. others, caſt vp their faces, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. others lie groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. ſome, humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſackcloath: <hi>Ionas.</hi> 3. ſome pray ſitting, as <hi>Elias. Kings.</hi> 19. ſome ſtanding <hi>Luke.</hi> 18. ſome lying vpon their beds: as <hi>Ezekia.</hi> 1. <hi>King:</hi> 20. Theſe indeed be the ſignes of an humble minde: for as one ſaith, <hi>Humiliatio cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, est ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humilitatis mentis: that the humility of the body, is a ſigne of the humbleneſſe of the minde:</hi> Yet it skilleth not how wee pray outwardly, either ſitting, kneeling, lying, walking, or ſtanding, ſpeaking or not ſpeaking for it is not the body that the Lord lookes vpon: neither is it the words that he doth reſpect: but it is the hart. If wee pray with an humble heart wee ſhalbe heard: pray after what manner we will pray. For (as <hi>Iſidorus</hi> ſaith in his booke <hi>de ſummo bono:) oratio cordis eſt non la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biorum, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim verba deprecantis, deus intendit: ſed orantis cor aspicit: melius eſt enim cum ſilentio orare, corde ſine ſono vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13560:23"/>
quam ſolis verbis ſine intuitu mentis. Prayer</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth not belong vnto the body but vnto the heart, neither is it the words of him that prayes, that the Lord doth marke: but he beholds the hart for it is better to pray with ſilence, with the heart without the voice: then with words with the voice, without the hart.</hi> And ſo much concerning the inuitation, both <hi>quid</hi> what wee muſt pray for: and <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo,</hi> how wee muſt aske; the promiſe followes: in which if you remember, I obſerued theſe two things: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſer: and the thing promiſed: in the promiſer: I obſerue alſo two things: his abilitie, in that he is able to performe, whatſoeuer he promiſeth: ſecondly his willingneſſe, that whatſoeuer he promiſeth he is willing to performe. And firſt of the abilitie of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, who is able to performe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he promiſeth. If wee do but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider with our ſelues, who the promiſer is, wee cannot make any doubt at all, of the thing promiſed: the promiſer is God, and not ſuch a God, who is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out motion, who hath no eares to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13560:24"/>
heare, no eyes to ſee, no tongue to ſpeake, no hands to giue: but ſuch a God, who heares all things, who giues all things, who ſees all things, who is able to doe all things, whatſoeuer him pleaſeth, both in heauen and earth: his name ſhewes his nature, he is powerfull <hi>Iehoua, Quod infinitum ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat; which ſignifies infinite.</hi> Infinite in greatnes, infinite in maieſtie, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in mercy, infinite in power, able to doe things impoſſible to mans capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and to bring that to paſſe, which the reach of man cannot imagine. The <hi>Hebrues</hi> call him <hi>Ethau; Quod fortem ſignificat; which ſignifies ſtrong, and mighty; Quoniam omnipotens est, becauſe he is Almighty:</hi> In Greeke he is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies <hi>Currens, running; quia vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> est, &amp; omnia implet ſua illa infinita eſſentia; becauſe at one time he is able to be, and is euery where, and with his infinite eſſence fill all places.</hi> And in Latine he is called <hi>Deus, à do, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>to Giue, quia omne datum optimum de ſurſum eſt, becauſe he is able to giue all good gifts, and becauſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13560:24"/>
euery good gift comes from him.</hi> He is <hi>Clemens &amp; miſericors ad dimittendum, potens ad auxiliandum, ad beatificandum copioſus: He is pittifull and mercifull, to forgiue; ſtrong and mighty to helpe; and to bleſſe most bountifull.</hi> He is called a <hi>Rocke,</hi> a <hi>fortreſſe,</hi> a <hi>ſtrong tower,</hi> a <hi>ſhield,</hi> a <hi>horne of ſaluation,</hi> a <hi>refuge,</hi> the <hi>Lord of hoſtes,</hi> able to deliuer vs from ten thouſand enemies: He is the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of great counſell, wiſdome</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> able to direct vs in all our conſultations. He is the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of the earth, and all that is therein; the world, and they that dwell therein, able to releeue vs in all our wants and neceſſities. He is the onely earthly and heauenly <hi>Phyſition,</hi> able to cure all our maladies: and he is the onely <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,</hi> able to ſuccour vs in all our miſeries. The gods of the Gentiles, be ſtocks &amp; ſtones: the gods of Papiſts, be crooked <hi>Crucifixes,</hi> which haue eares and heare not, eyes and ſee not, tongues and ſpeake not, the works of mens hands, the deuiſes of mens wit, made of baſe earth, of rotten wood,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13560:25"/>
of conſuming mettall: but our God is the Creator of the deuiſer of theſe gods, who is able and will confound theſe gods and god-makers. Our God hath eares to heare, and able to heare all in all places; eyes to ſee all in all countries; hands to giue, able to ſatisfie all that be in neede; whoſe hands be alwaies open to giue vnto them, which faithfully call vpon him. Let vs not therefore bee ſo ignorant with the Gentiles, as to pray vnto Idols; nor ſo wilfully blinde with the Papiſts, as to pray vnto Saints or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who be the creatures, of our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator: but let vs pray vnto the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Iehoua,</hi> the Lord of Hoſtes, who is onely able to helpe; who is only able to deliuer vs, in the time of trouble. <hi>Call vpon me</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 50 15.) <hi>in the day of trouble; ſo will I deliuer thee:</hi> Here is no mention of any Idol, here is no mention of any Saint or Angell; therefore let vs not turne the glory of the incorruptible God, to the ſimilitude of the image of a corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, of birds, of foure-footed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13560:25"/>
beaſts, &amp; of creeping things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.23 <hi>for curſed be the Image &amp; Image-maker Deut.</hi> 2.15. Neither let vs giue the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Creator vnto the creature, and direct our prayers vnto Saints or Angels, which we ſhould direct vnto God. For the Angell in the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which forbad <hi>Iohn</hi> to worſhip him, is able to ſatisfie a million of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and ſufficiently to proue vnto them, that neither Saint nor Angell is to be worſhipped. They know not when we pray, nor how we pray, nor how we pray, nor for what we pray: how can they then giue &amp; grant vnto vs, that which we pray for? there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angell or Virgin, nor Patriarke, Saint or Martyr (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtin.</hi> in his book <hi>de cura promat:) that knowes, more what we doe in earth, then we know what they do in heauen.</hi> Which he proues by this place of <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.16. <hi>Doubtles thou art our father, though Abraham be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of vs, &amp; Iſrael know vs not; yet thou ô Lord art our father and redeemer, thy name is for euer.</hi> There is neither <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> nor <hi>Iſaac,</hi> nor <hi>Iacob,</hi> neither any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13560:26"/>
Angell in heauen, knowes what we do vpon earth, more then God himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueales vnto them at ſuch time as he is to vſe them vpon his meſſage. If only God be our Lord, &amp; if he only is able to heare and ſee, and to releeue our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; then is he only to be called vpon, according to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandment of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come vnto me all yee that are weary and heauy laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> He is able and only able, to ſuccour vs in all our wants &amp; neceſſities: in the time of peſtilence, he is only able to ſend deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: in the time of famine, he is only able to ſend ſuſtenance: in the time of drought, he is only able to open riuers in the tops of hils, &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in the midſt of the vallies. When the poore and the needy ſeek for water (ſaith the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> 41.17, 18.) <hi>and there is none; ſo that their tongue faileth for thirſt. I the Lord will heare them, I the God of Iſrael will not forſake them, I will open the riuers in the tops of the hills, and fountaines in the midst of the vallies, I will make the wildernes as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13560:26"/>
a poole of water, and the waſte lands as ſprings of waters.</hi> Seeing therefore it is he &amp; he only, that can helpe and ſend releife, let vs with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> take him onely for our rocke, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, and <hi>Call vpon the Lord only who is only worthy to be praiſed.</hi> And as he is able, ſo he is willing; he is as willing to heare vs, as we are to cry; as willing to help vs, as we are to requeſt: he invites vs, he bids vs aske; and withall promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to heare vs, <hi>and it ſhall be giuen you,</hi> ſaith he: he is willing to heare vs, and therefore he bids vs aske; and becauſe we ſhould aske, he promiſeth to grant thoſe things that we do aske. God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth nothing, but that he would haue vs aske of him: and therfore he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it, becauſe we ſhould aske it. <hi>Deus</hi> (ſaith a Father) <hi>vult à ſe requiri quod pollicetur: &amp; ideo multa quae dare diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, prius pollicetur, vt ex promiſſione de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotio excitetur: God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>would haue vs challenge his promiſes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe things which he purpoſes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon vs, he first promiſeth, to ſtir vp our deuotion to pray for them. Ipſe facit vt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13560:27"/>
ipſum quaramus, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> invocemus: he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is the cauſe that we ſeeke vnto him, &amp; call vpon him.</hi> He calls vs and bids vs come, &amp; if we do come, he tells vs, that we ſhall haue, that for which we come. Come ye oppreſſed, come ye greiued, come yee diſtreſſed, come yee vexed, come all that are heauy laden, and yee ſhall haue eaſe, <hi>Come vnto me all ye that are heauy laden, and I will eaſe you:</hi> he cryes vnto vs, he makes proclamation, to the poore &amp; the needy, to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry &amp; thirſty, either corporally or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually: <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come vnto me, and I will ſatisfie him, Ioh.</hi> 6.35. he invites vs to come vnto him, that is, to pray vnto him; not once but many times; not in one place, but in many places. In the 26 of <hi>Mat: Watch &amp; pray</hi> (ſaith he): <hi>Pray continually,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17 <hi>Continue in prayer, Col.</hi> 4. <hi>Be ſober and watching in prayer,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.7. All which promiſes, &amp; all which places, ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, how willing the Lord is to helpe vs, when we pray, ſeeing he is ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that we ſhould pray, whenſoeuer we pray, and whatſoeuer we pray; for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13560:27"/>
he is at hand to help. For what nation is ſo great (ſaith <hi>Moſes) vnto whom the gods come ſo neere vnto them, as the Lord our God is neere vnto vs, in all that we call vnto him for? Deut.</hi> 4 7. yea, before we call vpon him, he will anſwer vs, and whil'ſt we ſpeake, he will heare vs, <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.24. Though he withdraw his hand from vs, for a time; we muſt not think, that his arme is altogether ſhortned, &amp; though a while he hide his face from vs, we muſt not think that he will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with vs for euer; for his arme is not ſhortned, that it cannot help; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth his anger indure longer then the twinckling of an eye. If he be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to plague vs, he is ſorry for our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions; and willingly would he help vs, if we would come for helpe vnto him: <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, thou that killest the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent vnto thee, how often would I haue gathered you together, as the hen doth her chickens, and you would not?</hi> As the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is willing to help her children, and the hen naturally her young ones: ſo is the Lord as willing to helpe thoſe, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13560:28"/>
willingly cal vpon him. He is ſo willing to heare vs, and to help vs in all our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, that if in our afflictions, we do doe not come vnto him, he is angry with vs, and layes the more croſſes and troubles vpon vs, to make vs more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, to ſeek vnto him. Thus he dealeth with vs, in the time of his plague &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation: thus he dealeth with vs in the time of famine: thus he dealeth with vs in the time of drought: thus he dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with vs, in the croſſes, plagues, and puniſhments, that he layeth vpon vs: he ſuffers them to tarry the longer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, &amp; to be more greiuous vnto vs, becauſe he being willing to help vs, we are vnwilling &amp; negligent in going vn to him for help. If the plague continue at any time any long ſeaſon in our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; if the windowes of heauen be long ſhut, ſo that the earth is dryed vp for lack of moyſture (as now of late it hath bin): let vs not thinke, that it is the Lords fault, and that he is vnwilling to heare vs when we pray: for indeed it is our owne faults; for either we do not pray at all; or elſe we prolong to pray; or
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13560:28"/>
elſe we mingle our prayers with mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings or grudgings, praying not as we ought to do: for if we do pray, and pray as we ought to do, the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, will heare vs without all faile; he will helpe vs, and for the time that he hath plagued vs, he will comfort vs, &amp; for the time of ſcarſitie, he will ſend vs a time of abundance: for the Lord will be found of thoſe that ſeeke him: if we ſeeke him, we ſhall be ſure to finde him <hi>Ego diligentes me ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligo,</hi> Prou. 8.17. <hi>I loue them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which loue me; and they that ſeeke mee early, ſhall finde me.</hi> Seeing therefore, that he would haue vs pray vnto him, and if we do not pray, when we ſtand in neede, he is offended: I ſay, as <hi>Caſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>odorus</hi> ſayes vpon the Pſalms, <hi>Iuſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est vt iugiter rogetur, qui ſi non peratur, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenditur. It is meete and requiſite, that we ſhould pray vnto him, ſeeing he is ſo willing to helpe vs; that if we neglect to pray, he is offended with vs.</hi> And alſo ſeeing the promiſes of Chriſt, both to giue and forgiue: to giue graces and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries; to forgiue ſins and offences,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13560:29"/>
be ſo many; and ſeeing he that hath power, it is he that hath promiſed; we may be fully reſolued of this point, that as he is able, ſo he is willing; and promiſing, he willingly will performe, whatſoeuer he promiſeth. And thus much of his abilite, &amp; of his willingnes, in that he is able to perform, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he promiſeth; &amp; in that whatſoeuer he promiſeth, he is willing to perform.</p>
            <p>Now I am to ſpeake of the thing promiſed, of the generalitie of it, in this word, <hi>It:</hi> then of the certainty of it, in this word, <hi>Shall, it ſhall be giuen you: Aske, and it ſhall be giuen you.</hi> And firſt of the generalitie of the gift: it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; he excepts nothing from vs, which is good for vs; if it be conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, it ſhall be giuen vs: be it what it will be, that we do aske; be it what it will be, that we neede, he can giue it vs, he can beſtow it vpon vs. <hi>Quicquid enim opus est ipſe habet: for whatſoeuer is neeedfull for man, he hath it,</hi> and whatſoeuer we can deſire, it is in his hand to giue: Wouldſt thou haue life, and doſt thou deſire to ſee long dayes? wouldſt thou
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13560:29"/>
faine go to heauen, and doſt thou not know the way? doſt thou deſire to ſearch the ſcriptures, and wouldſt faine be acquainted with the truth? aske them of God; he can giue thee them: he can giue thee life: he can ſhew the way vnto heauen, &amp; acquaint thee with the truth: for <hi>Ego ſum vita, via, &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas: He himſelfe is the way, the truth, &amp; the life, &amp; none can go vnto the father but by him, Ioh.</hi> 14.6. Doſt thou want the ſight of the body, the light of thine eyes, which is more pretious vnto thee then all the gold &amp; pretious things in the world? goe vnto the fountaine of light, go vnto God, &amp; he can giue thee it. <hi>Est enim lux à Deo ſplendens, vt inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſibilis dicatur: for he is a light ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſhining, that no mortall man can, or euer could, once behold or come neere him.</hi> Doſt thou want reaſon &amp; wouldſt faine haue vnderſtanding? <hi>Intellectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi> ſaith the Lord in the Pſalmes, <hi>I will giue thee wiſdom.</hi> If thou beeſt hungry, he is the bread of life; vnto whom if thou goeſt, <hi>thou ſhall neuer hunger, Ioh.</hi> 6.35. If thou beeſt thirſt, he is <hi>the true
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13560:30"/>
vine,</hi> of which whoſoeuer taſteth, ſhall neuer thirſt. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15 1. whereupon ſaith <hi>S. Amb: Chriſtꝰ via eſt o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nibꝰ ſi vulnera cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare deſideras, medicꝰ eſt: ſi fabribꝰ aeſtuas, fons eſt: ſi grauaris iniquitace, iuſtitia est: ſi auxilio iudiges viriꝰ eſt: ſi morie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times, vita est: ſi coetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſideras, vta eſt: ſi tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras fugis, lux eſt: ſi cibu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quaeris, alime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt. Chriſt is all vnto all: if thou art wounded and deſireſt to be healed, he is a phiſition: if thou art poſſeſſed with a burning feuer, he is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine wherein thou maiſt coole thee: if (with Mary Magdalen) thou haſt ſeuen deuills in thee, he is thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which must cleanſe thee from thy filthyneſſe: if thou beeſt oppreſſed, &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt one to ſuccour thee, he is thy power that muſt defend thee: if thou feareſt death, he is the life: if thou wouldeſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine heauen, he is the way: if thou flieſt darkneſſe, he is the light: &amp; if thou beeſt hungrie, he is thy food;</hi> therefore ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtin: cur per mult a vagaris homu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio, quaerenda bona anima &amp; corporis, quaere vnum bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in quo ſunt omnia bona, &amp; ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it: ibi enim eſt quicquid amas, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid deſideras, Wherefore doſt thou o man</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:13560:30"/>
(ſaith he) <hi>weary thy ſelfe in going about, ſeeking for the goods of the body and the ſoule, ſeeke one thing, which is Chriſt, in whom is all things, &amp; thou haſt enough: for in him is all things, that <hi>y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
                  </hi> loueſt, all things that thou deſireſt;</hi> &amp; he will deny thee nothing, that thou doeſt faithfully call vnto him for, he has all things, &amp; he can do all things; thou canſt not aske, that thing at his hand, which he will not grant thee, if with feruent prayer thou deſireſt it. For ſo great is the force of prayer, that ther is nothing that can withſtand it: if prayer once command it, be it a thing vnpoſſible, it muſt obey: contrary to all naturall reaſon; if <hi>Paule</hi> be in priſon and pray for deliuerance, the priſon doores muſt open of their owne accord: and his bands fall from him contrary to all expectation. The childe of God muſt haue deliuerance, or elſe the foundation of the priſon muſt be ſhaken by the power of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Acts.</hi> 16.26. <hi>If Peter</hi> be in priſon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother child of God, although he be kept &amp; watched, by two ſoldiers, bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with to chaines the priſon doores wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13560:31"/>
by two ſoldiers, bound with two chaines, the priſon dores watched by the priſon keeper: yet if the church, that is the children of God, pray for him: the angell of the Lord muſt come himſelfe, the child of God muſt be looſed, and <hi>Peter,</hi> (do the ſouldiers what they can with their we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, the bands what they can with their ſtrengths, the priſon doores what they can, with their bolts, &amp; the priſon keepers what they can with there nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe watching) muſt be deliuered, muſt go out of priſon conducted by the Angell, <hi>Act:</hi> 12.7. The <hi>Israelites</hi> being oppreſſed by the <hi>Philiſtins.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.8. they come to <hi>Samuell</hi> &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to pray, &amp; crie vnto the Lord for them: <hi>Samuell</hi> cried vnto the Lord; and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were deliuered as you may reade in the 10. <hi>verſe.</hi> The Lord ſent his thunder, which fought for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after a moſt wonderfull manner: that ſcattered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, that they all lay ſlaine before <hi>Iſraell.</hi> And <hi>Ioſua</hi> by his prayer: <hi>Ios:</hi> 18.14. made the ſun to ſtand ſtill in the firmament after it had runne his ordinarie courſe: he made it (I ſay)
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13560:31"/>
ſtand ſtill to giue him light, vntill hee had made an end of ſlaying his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>O potens praecatio! O powerfull prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er!</hi> that cammandes all things. It com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes the Angells in heauen, for at the prayer of <hi>Hezekia.</hi> 2. <hi>king.</hi> 19.35. The Angell of the Lord ſmote a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fowerſcore &amp; fiue thouſand of the ſouldiers of blaſpheming <hi>Saneherib</hi> in one night, ſo that in the morning they were all found dead corpſes. It com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes the heauens, for at the prayer of <hi>Elias</hi> the heauens were locked vp for three yeares, &amp; ſix months, ſo that no raigne fell vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth in all that time: &amp; againe he praied &amp; the heauen gaue raigne &amp; the earth brought forth her fruit. <hi>Iames.</hi> 5.17. It commands God <hi>iudgments:</hi> for at the prayer of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> the <hi>plague</hi> (that great iudgment of God) being begun among the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> ceaſed. <hi>Numb:</hi> 16.47.48. It co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth Gods afflictions: for at the prayer of <hi>Moſes Miriam</hi> was healed of her <hi>leproſie Numb.</hi> 12.14. And at the prayer of the man of God, <hi>Ieroboams</hi> hand that was dried vp, was reſtored. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 13.6. It commands the barren
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13560:32"/>
wombe, for <hi>Anna</hi> being childleſſe, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto the Lord, <hi>obteyned a ſonne:</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.20 It commands life, for at the praier of <hi>Eliah,</hi> the widdowes ſonne of <hi>Zarepthah</hi> being dead was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored vnto life. 1. <hi>King:</hi> 17. At the prayer of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> the <hi>Shunamites</hi> ſonne being dead <hi>was reuiued.</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 4.35. And at the prayer of <hi>Paule,</hi> the <hi>ſleeper,</hi> which fell downe dead, was caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way aliue. <hi>Act:</hi> 20.9. <hi>Superat tentame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta inimicorum, vincit demones, ſuperat immundos ſpiritus,</hi> It beats downe the temptations of our enemies, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes deuills, driues away vncleane ſpirits: <hi>&amp; dominum mundi flectere vota valent. Martial: lib.</hi> 8. <hi>epig: ad Domit.</hi> Praier commands God himſelfe, makes God obedient vnto mans voice: and when our praiers cannot come vnto Gods eares, it brings Gods eares vnto our prayers. <hi>Aske</hi> therfore <hi>and it ſhall be giuen thee,</hi> what ſoeuer thou doſt aske, his promiſe is generall: he will keepe nothing from thee, if thou do'ſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pray for it. Therefore in all thy needs &amp; extremities pray: pray &amp; thou ſhalt haue help. If thou beeſt in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13560:32"/>
pray for liberty, if thou beeſt oppreſſed, pray for ſuccour: if thou haſt enemies pray for deliuerance: if there be famine, pray for plenty: in the time of the plague, pray: if wee want raigne, pray: if thou art diſeaſed pray: if thou art afflicted, pray: if thou art child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, pray: if thou art tempted, pray: pray: &amp; thou ſhalt haue what thou wilt: for <hi>Aske, &amp; it ſhalbe giuen thee</hi> (ſaith chriſt). And ſo much for the generalitie, of the thing promiſed, which is laid downe in this word <hi>It, It ſhall be giuen you.</hi> Now a word or two of the certainty of it, and ſo I will conclude. If he were not able to giue vs thoſe things, which we aske, or if he were vnwilling to grant our deſires, then we might well feare the obtaining of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts; but he is able to help vs, &amp; he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to heare vs, as we haue heard in the two laſt points: if he were a ſtranger vnto vs, or an enemy againſt vs, that might breed ſuſpition in vs; or if he were only a familiar friend, or a neere kinſman, ſtill we might doubt of the matter: but he is no ſtranger, neither is he an enemy, for he is of our familiar acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with whom whenſoeuer we pray, we talk fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly: as <hi>S Aug:</hi> ſaith vpon the 85 Pſalm: <hi>Oratio tua locutia eſt ad deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do legis, deus ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13560:33"/>
loquitur: quando oras tu cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deo loqueris. Thy prayer</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a talking vnto God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou readeſt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſpeaks vnto thee: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou prayeſt, then thou talkeſt with God:</hi> Nay, he is not only our familiar acquaintance, but he is alſo nere vnto vs, as nere as poſſible can be: for he is our <hi>father:</hi> our <hi>father</hi> by <hi>creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> our <hi>father</hi> in <hi>education,</hi> our <hi>father</hi> in <hi>instructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> our <hi>father</hi> in <hi>compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> our <hi>father</hi> in <hi>correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> our <hi>father</hi> in <hi>adoption,</hi> as <hi>M. Boys</hi> wittily obſerues in his expoſition on the Lords prayer. He is our <hi>father,</hi> and therfore wiſheth vs well; he is our <hi>father</hi> in heauen, where there is all good things, &amp; nothing wanting, &amp; can giue vs all good things. Therfore I wil end, with this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of <hi>S. Bern: Nemo noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, parui pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dat oratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: dico cui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vobis, quod ipſe ad que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mꝰ, non parui pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dat ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: poſtqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> egreſſa eſt ab ore noſtro, ipſe ſcribit ipſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in libro ſuo: &amp; vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> è duobꝰ indubitanter ſperare poſſimus, quoniam aut dabit quod petimꝰ, aut quod novit vtiliꝰ. Let no man ſet lightly by his praier: for I ſay, that God doth great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly eſteem of it, after it is once out of our mouthes: &amp; doth write it in his book, &amp; without all doubt, we ſhall haue one of two; either we ſhall haue that, which we pray for; or elſe we ſhall haue that, that is more profitable for vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13560:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
